Guide to the John B. Lindner Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
John B. Lindner Papers
1949-1997
RG 208
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(8 boxes)
This collection documents selected activities of John B. Lindner, including his work with the National Council of Churches US/USSR Church Relations Committee, the "By Faith" project to prepare a video and book on the history of the ecumenical Christian student movement in the US, the Frontier Internship in Mission program, and projects related to Middle East policy and ecumenical formation.
Lindner, John B.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John B. Lindner, 2008-2013
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
John B. Lindner received a B.S. degree from Youngstown State University in 1970 and an M.Div from McCormick Theological Seminary in 1975. A minister in the Presbyterian Church, U.S.A., he spent over a quarter century providing leadership for international, ecumenical/interfaith programs of the PCUSA, the National Council of Churches (NCCCUSA) and the World Council of Churches (WCC). He served as writer for the NCCCUSA's Middle East Policy and directed its program of US-USSR Church Relations. He served the WCC as director of planning and development for the Ecumenical Institute at Bossey. Lindner served as Director of the Department for External Relations and Associate Dean for External Relations at Yale Divinity School from 2002 to 2013. Lindner is co-author of "By Faith: Christian Students Among the Cloud of Witnesses" (1991, Friendship Press) a history of the ecumenical Christian student movement in the US and co-issue editor of a special issue of the journal Theological Education (vol. 34, autumn 1997) on "Ecumenical Formation: A Methodology for a Pluralistic Age. The Case of the Ecumenical Institute at Bossey".
Scope and Contents
This collection documents selected activities of John B. Lindner, focusing on his ecumenical and interfaith work during the 1980s and 1990s. It provides a valuable record of the "on-the-ground" operations of organizations and programs that sought to advance and document ecumenical work.
Series I documents Lindner's work on the National Council of Churches US/USSR Church Relations Committee from 1983 to 1988. Memos, reports, and audio-visual materials document the work of the committee and the trips to Russia and visits from Russian church figures that it sponsored. Background material provides an overview of US/USSR church relations.
Series II focuses on the preparation of a video and book on the history of the ecumenical student Christian movement in America. The video was prepared for a national student gathering sponsored by the Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry in 1990. The book,"By Faith: Chrsitian Students among the Cloud of Witnesses" (1991), was edited by John B. Lindner, Alva I. Cox, Jr., and Linda-Marie Delloff. Numerous former leaders and participants in ecumenical student Christian movements were contacted to provide reminiscences, essays, and consultation in preparation of "By Faith." See also the Alva I. Cox, Jr. Papers (YDSL Record Group No. 179).
Series III documents Lindner's work on the International Coordinating Committee of the Frontier Internship program. This material provides a valuable complement to documentation of the Frontier Internship in Mission program found in the Margaret Flory Papers (YDSL Record Group No. 86).
Series IV relates to Lindner's work in preparing the 1980 Middle East Policy Statement of the National Council of Churches in the U.S.A. while Series V documents Lindner's work in the area of ecumenical formation.
Arrangement
I. National Council of Churches US/USSR Church Relations Committee
II. "By Faith" Project
III. Frontier Internship in Mission Program
IV. National Council of Churches Middle East Policy
V. Ecumenical Formation
College students -- Religious life -- United States -- Societies, etc. -- History; Interdenominational cooperation; Lindner, John B.
- National Council of Churches US/USSR Church Relations Committee, Series I
  - Committee records
    - Memos, minutes related to formation of committee, 1982 Oct - 1984 Mar (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Program proposal, report, memo, 1984 Apr-Nov (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Financial summary, proposal, memo, report, 1984 Oct-Dec, n.m. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Memos, minutes related to budget, 1985 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Proposals, memos, agenda, 1985 May-1986 Feb, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence between churches, 1985 Nov-1988 May, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5-A)
    - Other Committees: Children's Committee, Division of Overseas Ministries, U.S. U.S.S.R. Fit Committee, 1983 Dec- 1986 Dec (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Committee Collected Material: Report, Notes, Article, Newsletter, 1974 May-1988 Feb (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Programs and trips
    - 1983 Peacemaking Seminar to Russia: Schedule, Journal, Postcard, 1982 Oct- 1983 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1984 NCC Visit to Russia: Memos, Guidelines, Applications, 1983 Dec- 1984 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1984 Soviet Ecumenical Visit: Itinerary, List of members in delegation, 1984 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1985 Trip to Geneva Planning: Memos, Proposals, Program, 1985 Oct-Nov, n.m. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1985 Trip to Geneva: Memos, Programs from event, Statement of church leaders, Copy of sermon, 1985 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1985 Trip to Russia: Memos related to budget, Schedules, 1985 Mar-May (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1986 Trip to Russia: Memos, Schedules, 1985 Jul-1986 Nov (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1987 U.S. Soviet Summit Washington D.C.: Brochures, Prayer Pamphlets, 1987 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1987 Trip to Russia: Schedules, Participant Information, 1987 Mar-Jul (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1988 Trip to Russia: Memos, Participant Information, 1987 Dec-1988 Mar, n.m. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1988 Trip to Russia: Participant Information, Memos, Questionnaires, Schedules, 1988 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1988 Russia Trip: Participant Information, Briefing Manual, Schedules, 1988 Jun, n.m. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Russia Trips Background Material 1984-1987: Budget Information, History of U.S. U.S.S.R. Church Relations, 1984 n.m.-1986 Jun (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Russia Trips Background Material 1987: Reports, 1987 Feb (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Russia Trips Background Materials 1992: Participant Information, 1992 n.m. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Russia Trips Background Materials No Date: Song Books, Participants Directories, Russian Language Primer (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Russia Trips Background Information: Participant Information, participant manual (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - John Lindner Russia Notes: Personnel Information, Scheduling (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - John Lindner Russia Notes: Participant Information, Scheduling (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Collected material
    - Articles: 1983-1984, 1983 Sep-1984 Dec (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Articles: 1984-1985, 1984 n.m.-1985 Nov (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Articles:1986, 1986 Oct, n.m. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Articles: 1986-1988, 1986 Mar-1988 Mar. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Magazines: 1982, 1982 Jan, n.m. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Magazines: 1982, 1982 Jul-Oct (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Magazines: 1985, 1985, n.m. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Magazines: 1987, 1987 May-Dec (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Pictures, Brochures of Russia 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pictures, Brochures of Russia 1981, 1981 n.m. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Pictures, Brochures of Russia: 1982, 1982 n.m. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Pictures, Brochures of Russia: 1982, 1982, n.m. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Report U.S. Russia Relations: 1985, 1985 n.m. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Friendship Press Collected Material: Maps of Russia, USSR Christianity Magazine, 1987-1988 n.m. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Friendship Press Collected Materials: Children's Book: Christianity in USSR, Guide to Book, 1987 n.m. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Collected Material: Church Pamphlets, Pictures of Russia, 1983, n.m. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Newspaper Articles: 1974-1984, 1974 n.m.- 1984 Feb (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Newspaper Articles: No Date, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Prayer Books: 1980, 1980, n.m. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Orthodox Christianity Collected Material: 1971-1979, 1971-1979, n.m. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Audio Visual
    - Artifacts: Russian Calendar 1988, Pins, 1988, n.m. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Pictures of Russia Trips: Contact Negatives, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Pictures of Russia Trips: Contact Negatives, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Pictures of Russia Trips: Contact Negatives (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Pictures of Russia Trips: Developed Pictures,Slides 1984-1985, 1984 Jun-1985 Dec (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Beta Tape Unlabeled, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Discovering Our Oneness: Audio Cassette Tape and Photo Negatives (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Peacemaking Discovering Our Oneness Videotape, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sights and Sounds of the Churches of the U.S.S.R.: Audio Cassette Tape and Photo Negatives, 1987 Jun (Box 4, Folder 3)
- "By Faith" Project, Series II
  - Planning/correspondence
    - Summaries of project, grant proposal, ca. 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Lilly Endowment, potential project participants, draft outlines, 1990 Jul-Aug (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with contributors, 1990 Sep-Oct (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, consultation at Stony Point Center, 1990 Nov - 1991 Jan (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, report to Lilly Endowment, 1991 Feb - May (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Regarding use and study guides, letters of thanks to contributors, 1991 Jun-Nov (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Notes, budget, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Publications
    - Draft scripts for video, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Early drafts for introduction and chapter 1 of "By Faith: Christian Students among the Cloud of Witness", ca. 1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Early drafts of chapter 2, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Early drafts of chapters 3-5 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Early drafts of chapters 6-7 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Bound copy of chapter drafts, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Working proofs, 1991 Jun (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Final page proofs, 1991 Aug (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Video: "By Faith: Christian Students Among the Cloud of Witnesses" with study guide (VHS and DVD copies), 1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Publicity materials and review by John Boonstra, ca. 1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Research materials
    - Typescript essays and papers
      - By Robert Bilheimer, Adele Cloutier, John Deschner, Dan Dodson (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - By Paul Hilmer, Jean Lesher, Edward Nestingen, William Roy, Richard Schaull, Steve Schomberg, Samuel Slie, Franklin Woo (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Published articles
      - "Farewell UCM" by Leon Howell in "Humanity"; "The Student Christian Movement" in "Liberty and Justice for All: Racial Reform and the Social Gospel", 1969, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Publications of organizations
      - Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry, including program for "Celebrate" national ecumenical gathering of student Christian conference, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - National Student Christian Federation, ca. 1960 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Student Christian Movement (British), 1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - United Student Christian Council, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - University Christian Movement, 1967, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - World Student Christian Federation, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Notes /tapes
      - Typescript, including "Timeline of U.S. Campus Ministries History, 1706-1987"; "Alumni of the SCM in the United States", ca. 1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous handwritten notes by Lindner re. "In Faith" project, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Interviews (3 audiocassette tapes), ca. 1991 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Frontier Internship in Mission Program, Series III
  - International Coordinating Committee minutes, report, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Officers' meeting, seminar in Geneva, 1992 May (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - International Coordinating Committee meeting in Dakar, Senegal, 1992 Sep (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Blueprints": A Journal of Frontier Interns in Mission (two issues), 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "The Frontier Internship Program: A Ten-Year Evaluation, 1961-1971", including "An Overview After Ten Years" by Margaret Flory (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Reports related to internationalization of Frontier Internship program, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Transcript of telephone conversation with Margaret Flory, no date (Box 8, Folder 4)
- National Council of Churches Middle East policy, Series IV
  - Regarding preparation of Middle East policy statement, 1980 Feb-May (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Policy Statement on the Middle East and Study Document, 1980 Nov (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Articles and background material, 1978-1992 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Ecumenical Formation, Series V
  - Contents of special issue of "Theological Education" on ecumenical formation edited by Lindner, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 8)